<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thanksgiving sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, Court of Aldermen, sheriffs, and companies of the city of London at St. Mary-le-bow, April 16, 1696, upon occassion of His Majesty's deliverence from a villanous assassination in order to a French invasion by William Stephens ...</title>
            <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13589068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13589068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thanksgiving sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, Court of Aldermen, sheriffs, and companies of the city of London at St. Mary-le-bow, April 16, 1696, upon occassion of His Majesty's deliverence from a villanous assassination in order to a French invasion by William Stephens ...</title>
                  <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer ... and J. Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians III, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:1"/>
            <head>HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLON, <hi>MAYOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Jovis decimo Sexto <hi>Aprilis, 1696.</hi> Annoque Regni Regis <hi>Gulielmi, Angl.</hi> &amp;c. Octavo.</head>
            <p>THIS Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> to Print his Sermon Preach'd before the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Citizens of this City, at the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Mary-le-Bow,</hi> on <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 16th of <hi>April</hi> laſt, being the Thankſgiving Day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GOODFELLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Thankſgiving Sermon Preach'd before the Right Honourable THE Lord Mayor, Court of Aldermen, Sheriffs and Companies of the <hi>City of London,</hi> At St. <hi>Mary-le-Bow,</hi> April 16. 1696.</p>
            <p>Upon Occaſion of His MAJESTY'S Deliverance FROM <hi>A Villanous Aſſaſſination,</hi> In Order to a <hi>French Invaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM STEPHENS,</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Sutton</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhill;</hi> and <hi>J. Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>STEPHENS</hi>'s Thankſgiving Sermon Preach'd before the Lord Mayor, AT St. <hi>Mary-le-Bow,</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 16th. 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>JOHN HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLON,</hi> Kt. Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London;</hi> AND The Worſhipful the <hi>Court of Aldermen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE who at this day ſhall read the Account which our Annals give of the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion</hi> carried on againſt <hi>England,</hi> which is ſo well defended by her natural Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and where vaſt Numbers of Brave and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial People are never wanting, will conclude with himſelf, that <hi>Spain</hi> muſt have made ſure to her Intereſts no ſmall Party among us; from whoſe readineſs to cloſe with her Deſign, ſhe took confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to call her Armado <hi>Invincible.</hi> Without an Encouragement of this nature, 'twould be at all times a vain Attempt to Invade <hi>England.</hi> But this Motive was not then wanting; for the Queen was Excommunicated, and her Subjects freed from their Allegiance by the Pope, by whom her Dominions were alſo diſpoſed of to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who was therefore by the Papiſts (then a conſiderable part of the Nation) eſteem'd as King <hi>de Jure,</hi> whilſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> held only a bare Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100623:5"/>
            <p> But he who (an Age to come) ſhall read the Hiſtory of the late Embarkation, in order to a <hi>French Invaſion,</hi> and know that then the Papiſt was but the Two hundredth Man in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will admire from whence the <hi>French</hi> ſhould have drawn their Encouragement to make a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon <hi>England;</hi> the Name of KING <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM</hi> will then ſhine in the Hiſtory of this Age with a Brightneſs (at leaſt) equal to any of his Predeceſſors in the Sovereignty of theſe Realms; And the Knaviſh Diſtinction of <hi>De Facto,</hi> which was the Foundation-ſtone of the late deſigned Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſination, Inſurrection and Invaſion, will be left out of his Title.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhip knoweth, that thoſe who have refuſed to Swear Allegiance to His Majeſty, are but a ſmall Party, and the Papiſts are far from being any great one; ſo that the dead Weight which the <hi>French King</hi> muſt rely upon, are that Body of Men who own the King only as a bare Poſſeſſor of the Throne: To whom the Oath of Allegiance is (at beſt) but a meer Formality; very far from obliging them in Conſcience to a vigorous Aſſiſtance of the King. That they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (I mean) think no otherwiſe, always is made evident, when a Non-Swearer meets with one of the ſame Principle with himſelf, but yet who hath ſworn Allegiance. The firſt Queſtion is, Whether he hath ſworn Allegiance to the
<pb facs="tcp:100623:5"/>P. of <hi>O?</hi> 'Tis anſwer'd, Yes. 'Tis demanded for what reaſon; And 'tis replied, Becauſe he is now King of <hi>England.</hi> What Right hath he to the Crown of <hi>England?</hi> (ſaith the other, with ſome warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.) Truly, None (ſaith the Swearer,) but yet he is King <hi>de Facto.</hi> If Your Lordſhip is pleas'd to ſumm up theſe Anſwers, you will eaſily ſee if they amount to any more than this, <hi>viz.</hi> he hath ſworn Allegiance to the P. of <hi>O. Becauſe</hi> he is poſſeſſed of a Kingdom which of Right belongeth to another. I know that the Style of King <hi>William</hi> is allowed and uſed by theſe Men; but I am ſure that Your Lordſhip did not think the Regal Power of this Realm, to which the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England</hi> are entitled, could be ſolidly founded on a meer Complement, or rather Reproach.</p>
            <p>Nor is Your Lordſhip ignorant with what wonderful Zeal and Induſtry this weak Title (if it be any) was carried on. Not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by the way of Addreſs, but of meer Noiſe and Effrontery. So that whoſoever aſſerted His Majeſty's Right to the Crown, from the Peoples Grant in Parliament, was for ſo doing marked out as an Enemy to the Church and Monarchy. And thus the King's Dutiful Subjects have been diſcouraged, becauſe they own'd themſelves bound in Conſcience to ſupport his Rightful Title, whilſt the Right of King <hi>James</hi> was ſacredly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb facs="tcp:100623:6"/>and warmly defended by the <hi>De Facto</hi> Subjects of King <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could the <hi>French King</hi> have wiſhed for more inviting Advantages to the pretended King's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration?</p>
            <p>When I conſider the wonderful and undeſerved Deliverance which our good God, by his never failing Mercy, hath lately wrought for us; as I Congratulate the Joy of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> ſo I cannot omit to Congratulate a Treble Joy which particularly affecteth Your Lordſhip, ariſing from the Preſervation of the Metropolis, Admiralty and Bank of <hi>England,</hi> all which are Your Lordſhip's honourable and near Concerns. And that there may never be wanting Men of Your Lordſhips Abilities, and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Integrity to diſcharge the Truſts of the Nation, is the hearty wiſh of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most Obliged and most Humble Servant,</hi> William Stephens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100623:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>COL. III. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which alſo ye are called in one body: and be ye thankful.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMongſt the Characters which in antient Prophecy were given to the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 9.6.</note> one was that he ſhould be the <hi>Prince of Peace:</hi> He was born in a time that ſeldom hapned, when the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> was at peace with all the World; at his Birth the Angels, who were his Heralds, proclaimed <hi>peace upon Earth, and good will towards men.</hi> The Doctrine which he delivered, is juſtly ſtiled the <hi>Goſpel of Peace,</hi> becauſe all the Lines of it center in mutual Love and Charity; by which Peace is maintained in Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and within our Conſciences. His whole Life was a Pattern of the Peace of God, expreſſed in the moſt lively manner of Humility and Condeſcention: 'Twas indeed a daily return of Good for Evil; and his Death was the greateſt act of Charity which crowned all the former labours of his Love. But if there be no Herb ſo ſalutary, which a Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Creature cannot digeſt into Poyſon; 'tis not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that men of Corrupt Morals ſhould from the very Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Peace, draw Pretences to raiſe War, hatch Treaſons, Aſſaſinate and Maſſacre: Whilſt, on the contrary, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt do not only follow after Peace with all men, but ſeriouſly exhort all others to do the like. And this is the earneſt Exhortation of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church at <hi>Coloſs. Let the Peace of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By the Peace of God is meant a peaceable and condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temper of Mind, which ſweetens all our Actions both to our ſelves and others; whereby we caſt a favourable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100623:7"/>Eye upon what we diſcern in other men; being critical chiefly to find out the Beauty of every good Thought, and the Graces which attend the Words and Actions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This Moderation of Spirit towards men, is called <hi>the Peace of God;</hi> becauſe (1.) 'Twas the Great Deſign for which he made us (who are uncapable of bringing any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to him) that we ſhould be kind to one another. And, (2.) To the ſame end he Redeemed us, that being made Members of one Body, we ſhould be more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of each others condition. And, (3.) To this end he ſendeth his Holy Spirit into our Hearts to allay all Heat, and Bitterneſs, and Evil Zeal; to bridle our Paſſions, and moderate our Deſires, thereby ſetling the Peace of God in our Hearts. <hi>Let this Peace Rule,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Rule,</hi> in its Original, beareth relation particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the Office of a Judge or Umpire, who, by his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced, doth rule or determine any Caſe which is referred to his Arbitration. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth relation to the old Olimpick Games, wherein men ſtrove to outvy each other in manly Exerciſes, that they might gain a reward which was provided for him, who ſhew'd the greateſt degree of Manhood. Now when any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie aroſe between Competitors for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or reward, there was a Judge, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> appointed, who ſhould by his award over-rule and decide the Competition: And the word <hi>Rule</hi> in the Text doth ſignifie that particular Award, and is therefore reſtrained to a Rule of Court, by which Cauſes are determined.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine then, ariſing from the Text will be this, <hi>viz. A Charitable condeſcending temper of mind is the beſt Judge of all Controverſies, the beſt Moderator and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire of all Differences and Diſputes;</hi> or in ſhort, <hi>Charity is the beſt Court of Chancery.</hi> In purſuing this Subject I ſhall endeavour,
<list>
                  <item>1. To ſet forth the Truth of this Doctrine in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as may beſt recommend it to our practice.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100623:7"/>
                  <item>2. To ſet forth the Rules of this Court by which ſhe governs her Judgment. And,</item>
                  <item>3. To ſhew how far the Juriſdiction of this Court ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth, <hi>viz</hi> to all Chriſtians who <hi>are called in one body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. To ſhew that all the reaſons which oblige us to be thankful to God, particularly the occaſion of this preſent Solemnity, do enforce this Duty upon us. For ſo the laſt words of the Text <hi>be ye thankful,</hi> may be underſtood as a Motive to us to let the <hi>peace of God rule in our hearts.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Now a judgment of Charity for the determination of Controverſies cannot more effectually be recommended to us, than (1.) From the Example of God. (2.) From the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our Selves. And (3.) From the particular Felicity of this ſort of Judicature.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Example of God himſelf, who hath uſually in this Method put an end to thoſe Controverſies which have aroſe betwixt Mankind, his weak peeviſh Creature and himſelf, our great and good Creator. If we look back to the Creation, as deſcribed in the Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> we read that God beſtowed the whole World upon Mankind, only reſerving a ſmall peculiar to himſelf for a tryal of Man's obedience if he would ſatisfie himſelf with his own Portion, and reſtrain his Appetite at God's Command. We read alſo that from Man's indulging his Appetite, and not ruling it by his Reaſon, aroſe the firſt Controverſie betwixt him and his God. But this Breach was ſoon made up by Divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention. God did not exact the Life of Man on the day of his Tranſgreſſion: And tho' he condemned him to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, yet he allowed him to get Bread thereby, and an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to reliſh the Sweetneſs of it. He ſtill held forth the Lights of Heaven to direct him from without, and the Light of Reaſon to guide him from within. And to crown all, he revealed to him the way how he ſhould regain that ſtate of Immortal Happineſs from whence he had fallen.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance of this nature we read in the caſe of <hi>Lot,</hi> who being forewarned of the Judgment falling upon <hi>Sodom,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100623:8"/>and directed to fly to the Neighbouring Hills, yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts with God the place of refuge, and will accept only of one of his own chooſing.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.15, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe</hi> (ſaid the Angel of God) <hi>take thy wife, and thy daughters, and eſcape to the mountains, leſt thou be conſumed:</hi> to which kind admonition <hi>Lot</hi>'s an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, <hi>O not ſo, my Lord,</hi> &amp;c. and inſiſts upon <hi>Zoar</hi> to be the place of his refuge; and this Controverſie was ſoon ended by God's condeſcention,<note place="margin">v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>See, I have accepted thee concerning this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>3ly.</hi> What man was ever obliged by God in a higher manner than <hi>Moſes!</hi> who was deſigned his Special Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to <hi>Egypt,</hi> there to diſcharge the true Character of an Hero, in being the Deliverer of his Countrymen from ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. For this Office God qualified him with the power of working Miracles; thereby ſetting the Broad-Seal of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Commiſſion, and promiſing alſo to aſſiſt him with ſuch Eloquence as ſhould become the Meſſage which he was to deliver; yet after all, <hi>Moſes</hi> peremptorily refuſeth to obey theſe honourable Commands,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.13, 14.</note> ſaying to God, <hi>Send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt ſend.</hi> This Anſwer did indeed <hi>kindle the anger of the Lord againſt Moſes;</hi> but his Compaſſion allay'd his Anger; and ſoon after he confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him in his Commiſſion, and ſtrengthneth him with the aſſiſtance of his Brother <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 15, 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Towards whom we likewiſe read a ſignal inſtance of God's condeſcention, in healing up a wide breach made by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of that High-Prieſt: Who, whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was upon the Mount,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.20.</note> 
               <hi>changed the glory of Iſrael into the ſimilitude of an Ox, that eateth graſs.</hi> How great a Controverſie might God have had with him, who being the High-Prieſt of the Living God, would yet draw all <hi>Iſrael</hi> into a party to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a Lifeleſs Idol. Who ſoon after God had delivered them from the Houſe of Bondage, ſhould ſet up <hi>Egyptian Idolatry</hi> to betray the people of the Lord back into their former ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, and ſlavery. How juſtly might God have made him reſemble his Idol, by taking away ſight from his Eyes, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100623:8"/>from his Ears, and breath from his Noſtrils! But ſee the compaſſion of God to paſs by <hi>Aaron</hi>'s ſin, and ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue him in his high ſtation.</p>
            <p>'Twould be endleſs to number the many Controverſies which God had with his murmuring People in their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards <hi>Canaan:</hi> Which were yet alldetermined by the forbearance and long-ſuffering of the Moſt High. And doubtleſs from God's great condeſcention to <hi>Moſes</hi> (before mentioned) he learned to bear with the peeviſh murmurings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt his Adminiſtration in the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>But there was never ſuch an angry man as <hi>Jonah,</hi> who being by God commanded to go to <hi>Ninive,</hi> (and be the Herauld of his Judgment in order to prepare that great City to prevent its actual falling upon them) fled to <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiſh,</hi> which lay the contrary way to that which he was ordered to take. Yet inſtead of a ſevere puniſhment, God gave him a miraculous preſervation; and after that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd him in his Prophetical Office.<note place="margin">Jona. 3.1.2</note> For we read that <hi>the word of the Lord came to Jonah the ſecond time, ſaying, ariſe go unto Ninive, that great City, and preach unto it the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I bid thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this reſpect Jeſus Chriſt ſhewed himſelf to be the expreſs Image of the Father, when with a ſteady reſolution he endured ſo great a contradiction of Sinners; which tho' it rendred him a man of Sorrows, yet could never hinder him from ſhewing compaſſion to thoſe who were the cauſes of his ſufferings: <hi>When he was led as a Lamb to the ſlaughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.7.</note> 
               <hi>he was dumb as a ſheep before her ſhearers, and opened not his Mouth:</hi> unleſs it were to recommend his Enemies to God's mercy. In which prayer he ended his controverſie with them, together with his Life, <hi>Father, forgive them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23.34.</note> 
               <hi>for they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we conſider the particular Controverſies which Chriſt had with two of his Diſciples, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> they were ſoon compromized by his gracious condeſcentions. Thrice <hi>Peter</hi> had deny'd his Maſter, who after that confirm'd him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100623:9"/>in his Apoſtolick Function by a threefold Benediction. And tho' <hi>Thomas</hi> was ſo obſtinately prejudiced againſt the belief of Chriſt's Reſurrection, that he would give no credit to the Relation of his Fellow-diſciples, whoſe probity was ſo well known to him, but he muſt be convinced by his ſenſes alone, he muſt feel out the Article of the Reſurrection in the Side of his Maſter;<note place="margin">Joh. 20.25.</note> (for thus he ſaith, <hi>Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and thruſt my hand into his ſide, I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi>) Yet in this caſe our Saviour condeſcended to ſatisfie his unbelieving Diſciple in his own way. <hi>Reach hither</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thy finger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 27.</note> 
               <hi>and behold my hands: and reach hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy hand, and thruſt it into my ſide. And be not faithleſs but believing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>2d</hi> Reaſon which recommends Charity to rule our Hearts, and direct our Judgments, is the conſideration of our own ſelves, with relation to the lapſed ſtate of our Nature: which is ſo prone to evil, that we dare not ſuffer our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be tried in a Court of ſtrict Juſtice. But we always find it neceſſary to appeal to Equity, and a favourable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Do we not find recorded in Holy Writ, not only the ſlips and failures, but groſs faults committed by men of high Characters. So that the man after God's own heart might have reaſon to ſay, with relation to men as well as God, <hi>if they ſhould mark wherein he had done amiſs, he could not be able to abide their judgment.</hi> And let any man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſtate of his own ſoul, and he will find reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to condemn himſelf. He who ſeeth a Mote in his Brother's Eye, if he would look homewards, might diſcern a Beam in his own;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.</note> and <hi>therefore</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>thou art inexcuſable, O man, that judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf: for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame things.</hi> Nay, in all reſpects, we may ſay we do the ſame thing, to far forth as God is concerned in the ſins of men. For tho' one ſinneth againſt the Laws of Juſtice, another againſt the Rules of Charity, a third againſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100623:9"/>yet they all ſhew the ſame diſreſpect to God's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. They are all guity of the ſame Ingratitude to God who hath laid ſtrong obligations on them all to duty; and of the ſame Infidelity with regard to the terrors of the Law, and rich Promiſes of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Where is the man who would be contented to have a Window into his Breaſt? Why then does any man by being a ſevere Critick upon his Brother, tempt him to judge as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely as he has been judged, and to pay back that hard meaſure which was meeted out to him?</p>
            <p>But this conſideration ought to be improved further from the common deficiency found in our Intellectuals as well as Morals: whereby we are rendred inſufficient to paſs ſtrict judgment on the ways of others; eſpecially ſince we are utter ſtrangers to their Hearts from whence the ſprings of all actions ariſe. As to outward Circumſtances, Satan may appear as an Angel of Light, whilſt the true Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light ſeem as <hi>the filth of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>and the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of all things.</hi> 'Tis hard for man throly to diſcern even his own heart: and if we judge by outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, we are not likely to judge righteous, unleſs it be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe charitable, judgment.</p>
            <p>But how various are the ſizes of human Capacities, and the ſhapes of our formed and laſhioned underſtandings? Not one man's Mind, any more than Face, perfectly reſembling another in all its Lines and Features. And yet the weaker Capacity will moſt commonly be judging the ſtronger; as if the ſmaller meaſure could comprehend the greater. And altho' God hath been pleaſed to reveal his Wiſdom to men, tho' <hi>he who hath commanded the light to ſhine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.7</note> 
               <hi>hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the enlightning know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God's glory in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh,) yet he telleth us, that <hi>we have this knowledge in earthen veſſels.</hi> Subject to many frailties, beſides the ill tincture of the earth which contains it. What ſtrong and almoſt invincible prejudices are mixed even with our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100623:10"/>of God and his Son Chriſt Jeſus, the various Sects of Chriſtians ſufficiently ſet forth. How eaſily do preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices ariſe from the cuſtom of the place where we live? the examples of thoſe we converſe with? the admiration we have for mens perſons? from the byas of affection towards ſome, and averſion to others, according to the real or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary good or ill turns they have done us? what various forms, and different ſhapes doth Education give to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity? ſo that the very Sheep of Chriſt do not ſo much as know one another, but one part of the Flock ſhall flie from the other. Now all their ſtrict and rigorous cenſures againſt one another can never be juſt; and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally none of thoſe ſevere judgments are ſo. And ought therefore give place to the favourable conſtruction of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſuffer the peace of God to bear Rule.</p>
            <p>The <hi>3d</hi> Conſideration which recommends Charity as the the beſt Chancery to end all differences amongſt Chriſtians is the extraordinary Felicity of this Court of Equity. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, (1.) it gives the quickeſt diſpatch to buſineſs. And (2.) it decideth all Controverſies to the mutual ſatisfaction of both parties. As to the firſt of theſe, Charity cutteth off all occaſions of delay; it admits no Demurrers, Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Rebutters. Charity inſiſteth not upon ſtrict Fend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Provings,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> but rather <hi>ſuffereth long, and is kind, and thinketh no evil:</hi> but admits of as good colours as the Advocate can put upon the Actions of his Client:<note place="margin">v. 4, 5.</note> for <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity believeth all things, and hopeth all things, i. e.</hi> believeth and hopeth the beſt of all things; and whenſoever the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender pleadeth Guilty, the Proceſs is ſtopped; and then both parties are ſatisfied: the one that he hath found favour, the other that he hath granted it. One is delivered from fear, the other from trouble; both rejoyce that their Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is happily brought to an end. And to crown all, it ſometimes falls out, that each hath made a Friend of the other.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100623:10"/> 2. The Second general Head to be conſidered, was the Rules of this Court by which ſhe governeth her Judgment. Now the Rules and Meaſures conſtantly us'd in Courts of Judicature, are thoſe Methods and Ways which long Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath found out to be uſeful and expeditious for determining of Cauſes. By theſe our Courts give Law to their own Power, in order to the publick Good. And the Rules by which Charity decideth Controverſies are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Charity judgeth not the Perſon of any Man, from thoſe ill Conſequences which are charged upon his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; eſpecially if he diſown thoſe Conſequences: Since <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what cometh from within can defile the Man.</hi> A good Man will reaſon thus with himſelf: 'Tis poſſible I may be miſtaken in the Inferences I draw from ſuch an Opinion: Or, if I have concluded right; another, who receiveth the Opinion, it may be, doth not diſcern the ill Conſequences of it; but if he declare his Disbelief of 'em, though they may be ever ſo truly charged upon the Opinion, they cannot upon the Man: This Rule of Charity would calm the Diſputers of this World, and ſoften the Stile of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie. 'Twould ſuffer no Gall to drop from the Pen of the Writer in bitter Reflections upon the Perſon of his Adverſary.</p>
            <p>This Rule would have ſoftned the Controverſie, and prevented the Quarrel which not long ſince aroſe betwixt the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians;</hi> the one call'd the other Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willers, and from thence laid to their Charge that they leſſened the Eſteem due to the Grace of God, as if it were not abſolutely neceſſary to our Salvation; when on the other hand it was objected to them who held the Article of abſolute Predetermination, that they blaſphemed God by making him the Author of Sin. Now, tho' the one Party owned God's Grace abſolutely needful to their Salvation, and moſt of the other Party diſowned God's being the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100623:11"/>of Sin; and all diſowned that he was culpably ſo, yet an immortal Hatred aroſe between both Parties, and when each had the Opportunity of Power the other felt the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Court eſteemeth Errors in Men's Judgment not to be a Subject Matter of Puniſhment, but Inſtruction, <hi>Errantis poena eſt doceri.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Such Opinions which are meerly ſpeculative, tending to no immoral Practice, (whether they be true or falſe) are innocent, and can therefore give no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Diſturbance, and conſequently no juſt Occaſion of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing their Abettors. They fall not under the Cognizance of the Ruler,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>who is only a Terrour to evil Works, a Revenger to execute Wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi> Had this Rule been obſerved, <hi>Smithfield Fires</hi> had never been kindled, and the World had been guiltleſs of all the barbarous Murders of thoſe who held this innocent Opinion (could it poſſibly have been an Error) <hi>viz.</hi> That what was Bread before the Conſecration of the Prieſt, was Bread after it.</p>
            <p>But if a Man will propagate ſuch erroneous Opinions which directly miſlead Men into wicked Practices, the publick Weal requireth that an effectual Reſtraint be put thereunto; as in the Caſe of a Native of <hi>England,</hi> who hath received Orders from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by Law condemned to Death, the reaſon is becauſe no Prieſt is admitted to Cure of Souls under that See, but is obliged to take an Oath contained in the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th, <hi>Super formam juramenti profeſſionis,</hi> which is uſually annext to the printed Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which Oath contains in it evident Matter of Treaſon, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by theſe Clauſes: <hi>Romano Pontifici veram Obedientiam ſpondeo &amp; juro,</hi> i. e. I vow and ſwear true Obedience to the Pope. Again, <hi>Caetera omnia à ſacris Canonibus &amp; oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menicis Conciliis definita recipio,</hi> i. e. all the Decrees and Determinations of general Councils and holy Canons I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; and at laſt, <hi>hanc fidem integram indubitanter recipio, &amp; ab illis quorum Cura ad me ſpectabit, teneri, doceri, &amp;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100623:11"/>praedicari, quantum in me erit curaturum juro,</hi> i. e. as I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily receive theſe Doctrins, ſo I ſwear that I will take care, to the utmoſt of my Power, that they ſhall be propagated whereſoever I ſhall be concerned.</p>
            <p>Now, ſince thoſe Canons, which the Papiſts call holy, and Councils which they call general, give the Popes a Power to depoſe Sovereign Princes: And ſince the Experience of our own Nation hath informed us that former Popes have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to render the Imperial Crown of this Realm feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory to <hi>Rome,</hi> and that K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were actually excommunicated and depoſed by papal Power, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſuch Natives of <hi>England,</hi> who ſwear to propagate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins of this Tendency among their Countrymen, and alſo vow and ſwear perſonal Obedience to the Pope in Matters of this nature, can be conſider'd by our Laws no otherwiſe than as Traytors to their Country. I know the Papiſts complain that their Prieſts ſuffer here for Religion and the Catholick Faith; but if what they are pleaſed to call by thoſe Names be in Truth Treaſon of the higheſt Nature,<note place="margin">The burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Men alive upon the ſcore of Religion is by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts called an Act of Faith.</note> I do not ſee how ſpecious Names can excuſe the Guilt of ſuch execrable Villany any more than the fine Phraſe, <hi>An Act of Faith</hi> can excuſe the moſt barbarous Sort of ſolemn Murder, which is the burning of Men alive, againſt whom they pretend not to lay the Charge of any Immorality.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, if the Opinions which ſome Man or Society of Men profeſs, have in their Nature no Tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to produce immoral Practices betwixt Man and Man, nor to unſettle the Form of Government which is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Nation; this Court of Chancery hath no Rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to puniſh ſuch Opinions, notwithſtanding the Complaints of ſome angry Men of all Communions who ſhall charge him that profeſſeth any Opinion they diſlike, with a Breach upon the Peace of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Court forbid deth no Man or Community of Men, that Liberty in the Exerciſe of their Chriſtian Profeſſion which Chriſt hath not forbidden. Nor will it compel any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100623:12"/>one by Fine, Impriſonment, bodily Pain, or any other Force whatſoever, to own any Article of Belief, or joyn with any Form of Worſhip, which he in his Conſcience doth diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove. The reaſon hereof is, 1. Becauſe our Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion teacheth us to call no Man Maſter but Chriſt; and, 2. Becauſe there is no Aſſembly of Men; no not a <hi>general Council, but may err</hi> (as our Church declareth in her 21ſt Article) <hi>even in things pertaining unto God.</hi> 3. Becauſe our Reaſon was given us to interpret the Scriptures for our ſelves, not to be a ſtanding Rule to others: And, 4. if the Reaſon of the learned cannot convince, much leſs can the Force of the Magiſtrate. But on the contrary, put Force in the Place of Reaſon, and all Religion will be alike, and as Colours in the dark, undiſtinguiſhable. Force in its own Nature equally diſpoſeth a Man to become Mahometan, Chriſtian, or Pagan: Not that it can convince Men of any Truth which is in theſe Profeſſions; but it may compel 'em, thro' Hypocriſie, to make a Shew of any Religion.</p>
            <p>Had this Rule of our Court been obſerved, Pope <hi>Victor</hi> had never put the World into a Flame by enjoyning the Day upon which the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> was to be celebrated; which Controverſie produced ſuch an unchriſtian Bitterneſs that the Eaſtern and Weſtern Chriſtians withdrew from the Communion of each other. I cannot conclude this Point better than with the excellent Words of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> or Book of Peace, written heretofore to compoſe the Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in our Church by the preſent Right Reverend Biſhop of of <hi>Worceſter. Were we</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſo happy but to take off things granted unneceſſary by all, and ſuſpected by many, and judged unlawful by ſome; and to make nothing the Bonds of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion but what Chriſt hath made ſo; allowing a Liberty for Matters of Indifferency, and bearing with the Weakneſs of thoſe who cannot bear thoſe things which others count lawful; we might be reſtored to a true primitive Lustre, far ſooner than by furbiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſome antiquated Ceremonies which can derive their Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree no higher than ſome ancient Cuſtom and Tradition;</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100623:12"/>after this he piouſly concludeth, that <hi>God will one Day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince Men, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Church lieth more in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Faith and Affection, than in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of doubtful Rites and Ceremonies,</hi> p. 123.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Court takes into ſpecial Cognizance, all the Bonds of Union, as well as Cauſes of Diviſion which may be found amongſt Chriſtians. For want of this impartial Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Men are apt to think the Differences betwixt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be wider than indeed they are; and from hence chiefly it is that the deplorable Differences amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are ſtill maintained. There is not any one Doctrin or Practice neceſſary to make us good Men here, or happy hereafter, but what we are all agreed in. The Moral Law of Chriſt is equally receiv'd by us all, and the Apoſtles Creed, which containeth a Summary of our Evangelic Faith, is own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us all. Idolatry and Superſtition are caſt out of the ſeveral Forms of Worſhip which all thoſe Proteſtants, who diſſent from us, adhere to. Now theſe Bonds of Union, ſo many in Number, ſo ſtrong and important in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, cannot but prevail upon a charitable Diſpoſition, to compromize thoſe few Differences which ariſe from various Ways of Expreſſion, Rites of Worſhip, or Forms of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which are Matters of no great Importance, if conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by themſelves; but if compared with the Fundamentals, in all which we are agreed, they will ſcarce be diſcernible by the Judgment of Charity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This Court puts the beſt Conſtruction upon all caſes which come before it; 'twill admit of no Innuendo's, ſtrain'd Aggravations ariſing from meer Probabilities or fanciful Conjectures. Plainneſs of Senſe is here better underſtood than Sharpneſs of Wit: It looks upon the beſt Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be the right Handle of the Cauſe, according to which it giveth Judgment. This Rule was taught by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Behaviour to his Diſciples on that Night in which he was betray'd: At that time when the Troubles and Cares of the Maſter increaſe, the Diligence of the Servant ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100623:13"/>be doubled. But ſo heavy were his Diſciples, that they did not watch with him an hour in his Extremity of Grief: But whilſt the Maſter was in an Agony, the Servants were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned, that they fell aſleep. Yet Chriſt put the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction hereupon; not blaming their negligence, but in compaſſion to their Humane Frailty, he pronounced this Sentence;<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit indeed is willing, but the Fleſh is weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third general Conſideration was the Extent of this Court's Juriſdiction; which reaches as far as the Body of Chriſt extends. <hi>To this we are called in one Body,</hi> ſaith the Text. Humane Nature obligeth us to compaſſionate Men as Men. But when it pleaſeth God to diſtinguiſh a People from the reſt of the World, and take them for his own Lot, by revealing himſelf particularly to them, he doth oblige them to a cloſer tye of Love to each other in anſwer to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar condeſcenſion he hath ſhewn to them. Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> was obliged to a ſtricter Charity towards their Brethren than to Strangers from them in point of Religion; but yet they were to extend their utmoſt Compaſſion to all Proſelytes, let them come over to their Religion from what Nation ſoever.</p>
            <p>In like manner Chriſtians are by St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>as they have opportunity to do good unto all men, but eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of Faith.</hi> So that as every Nation and Government is by a true Civil Polity obliged to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar care of all the Parts and Members belonging thereunto; and every part and Member of that Body Politick is oblig'd to uſe his utmoſt endeavour for the good of the whole, ſo all People who are united under one Head the Lord Jeſus, ſhould look upon themſelves as one Body; and therefore every diviſion and branch thereof ſhould in Chriſtian poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hold it ſelf oblig'd in particular manner to contribute to the ſafety of the whole; all one as every individual Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a Family is bound in a more eſpecial manner to ſupport the common Intereſt of their own Houſhold, more than any other. To exerciſe this Charity, to the Rule of this Peace of God, we are called in one Body.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100623:13"/>
            <p> The outward viſible bond of Union which joineth this Body together is the pure Law of Chriſt, unmixed with the Traditions of Men; not levened with any Worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. That Law which teacheth us to know that God alone is our Owner, Governor, and Benefactor, and therefore to him chiefly belongs our Submiſſion, Obedience, and Thankfulneſs. Which enjoyneth us Sobriety, Juſtice, and Charity: And hath no other Deſign, but to adorn our Souls with all ſorts of Virtue in as eminent Degree as we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of receiving. All the Profeſſors of this Law, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſperſed over the World, are Members of this one Body, and may therefore demand the utmoſt aſſiſtance of our Chriſtian Charity.</p>
            <p>This Rule of Charity was well underſtood in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Reformation, and was held as a Maxim of State during the happy Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of ever bleſſed Memory, viz. <hi>That</hi> England <hi>ſhould always make it ſelf the Head and Protection of the whole Proteſtant Intereſt.</hi> Our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church or Nation (call it which you pleaſe) ſaw it ſelf particularly oblig'd to this undertaking by the eſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, which furniſhed us with that Strength, Wealth, happy Situation, and Fertile Soyl which rendred us the Envy and Terrour of Antichriſt. And hence was it that our Church looked upon her ſelf in relation to other Proteſtant Churches as the Elder Siſter in the Family, who being grown up to greater Strength and Abilities than the reſt, diſchargeth the part of a Mother, in giving her Aſſiſtance to the Younger and more tender Branches of that Houſhould. By purſuing this Pious State Maxim, <hi>Englands</hi> Glorious Queen made her ſelf the Nurſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the whole Goſpel-Reformation; hereby ſhe gave check to the power of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and by making all true Proteſtants, <hi>i.e.</hi> all true Chriſtians her Friends, ſhe enabled <hi>England</hi> to make good her Oldeſt Maxim of State, which was, <hi>To keep the ballance of Europe equal and ſteady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it is evident, if the Line which Succeeded
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100623:14"/>that great Queen had Religiouſly purſued the Holy Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick of her Reign, <hi>Europe</hi> had never heard of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown greatneſs of <hi>France,</hi> much leſs ſubmitted to thoſe Barbarous Inſolencies which ſome places now groan under. Nor had <hi>England</hi> at this day been ſtartled by Popiſh Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats, who were to prepare the way for a French Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. So that our Allies of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion muſt allow this Proteſtant Maxim to be truly Catholick, becauſe their ſafety from the Power of <hi>France</hi> was wrapped up in it together with our own. And hence it may be diſcern'd, who amongſt us are trueſt Proteſtants and beſt Engliſh-men: Thoſe who endeavour to heal up all Differences amongſt Chriſtian Churches who are willing to join with them in bonds of Affection as Fellow-members of the ſame Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith, or thoſe who by vilifying all Foreign Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and all other Communions but their own, divide the Body of Chriſt, and the Affections of Chriſtian Churches from one another.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid alſo 'tis evident, that the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Anti-Chriſt can be no part of that One Body men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my Text, and no more within the perview of our Chriſtian Law of Charity, than Turks and Infidels. I have read in the Turkiſh Alcoran ſome honourable mention of Jeſus the Son of <hi>Mary;</hi> but tho' the <hi>Mahometans</hi> join with us in paying ſome fort of Reſpect to our Saviour, yet ſince they pay a greater Deference to their own Prophet, and an intire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Laws, and ſince their Laws have inſpir'd them with the Genius and Spirit of their Prophet, which never faileth to exert itſelf in the higheſt degrees of Rage and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt all who profeſs an intire ſubjection to the Lord Jeſus; I do not remember that the Moſque hath ever been owned as a branch of the Chriſtian Temple.</p>
            <p>And altho' the State-politick Confederacy of <hi>Rome</hi> erect Temples and Altars to Chriſt (tho more to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) yet in as much as they pay a more profound Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their own High Prieſt, and the Laws which he hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100623:14"/>confirmed, and ſince the Genius and Spirit of thoſe Laws is ſo directly oppoſed to the good Spirit of the Goſpel, that there is no Rebellion or Inſurrection ſo bloody, no Murder or Maſſacre ſo cruel, no Conſpiracy or Aſſaſſination ſo baſe and barbarous, but what the Spirit of Popery not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, but injoyneth in Oppoſition to thoſe who own no High-Prieſt but the Lord Jeſus, it cannot eaſily be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended how the Maſs-houſe ſhould be any part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church; altho' the Papiſts aſſume to themſelves, in excluſion of all others, the Sacred Name of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And in this they are follow'd by their Adherents among us, tho' of another Denomination, who chuſe to ſerve <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> for the ſake of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and to preſerve our holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church in its original Purity joyn themſelves to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. This is indeed a Combination without precedent; the Fundamental of their Faith is Contradiction, and their Principles would beſt have been explained by the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, who read Lectures concerning the blackneſs of Snow. I have heard of a crazed Friar, (the fore-runner of theſe men) who made his Prayer to God to reconcile himſelf to the Devil, in order to eſtabliſh Peace in the world: juſt as this ſort of Men aſſiſt <hi>French</hi> Dragoons into the Kingdom, Popiſh Cut-throats into the Court, and the late Subverter of our Religion and Laws into the Throne; and all this, in order to ſupport the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which Church does therefore caſt them out as Apoſtates from her Communion.</p>
            <p>But if there ſhall be found within the pale of our holy Church any Abettors of theſe Adherents, who ſhall ſtill be diſputing our gracious King <hi>William</hi>'s Right to the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Throne, who, by divine Aſſiſtance, firſt recovered and does ſtill ſupport all the Rights of theſe Kingdoms, tho' this ſort of men take great pains to ſequeſter themſelves from our Chriſtian Charity, yet I truſt, that God in his great mercy will continue to blaſt all the deſigns of Antichriſt, confound the Stratagems of <hi>Rome,</hi> diſcover the Treacheries of <hi>France,</hi> and proſper the Arms of our Rightfull and Lawfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100623:15"/>King <hi>William,</hi> that his happy <hi>Succeſs</hi> and our ſecure <hi>Settlement</hi> may be even to theſe men as a divine Illumination.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The fourth general Head, was the great motive to Chriſtian Charity, which in the Text is taken from our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to thankfulneſs, <hi>be ye thankfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot reflect upon any one reaſon, which engageth us to be thankfull to God, but what obligeth us to Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards one another. Our Creation, Preſervation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Means of Grace, Hopes of Glory, and all the Bleſſings of this Life, for which we give daily Thanks, are either common Bonds of Union, or Talents to be employ'd for common good. But how particular a motive to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity the wonderfull Deliverance which God hath ſo lately wrought, doth aſſord us, will appear, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Particulars thereof, ſo far forth as they have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been diſcovered: as firſt, The Deliverance of a Life as dear to us as the breath of our Noſtrils, from a barbarous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſination: and ſecondly, Of our Nation from an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inſurrection in order to aſſiſt a <hi>French</hi> Invaſion. All the parts of this Conſpiracy were linked together in one Chain; the Aſſaſſination was to facilitate the Inſurrection, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to make way for the Invaſion, and all this in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a <hi>French</hi> Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>If any private perſon hath received injury from another, there is in all civiliz'd Countries a Law and Court of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, from whence the Appellant may receive a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; ſo that there is no room left for any private Revenge; much leſs for that which is in the higheſt degree barbarous, as is an Aſſaſſination upon the meaneſt perſon. If a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ariſeth between Sovereign Princes, their Appeal lieth to God's Providence, and is to be proſecuted by open force of Arms. ſo that hereby is a bar ſet to all pretence for an Aſſaſſination upon any publick perſon; and indeed no men ever pretended to aſſaſſinate, but ſuch who had openly caſt off all principles of Humanity; ſuch as, Houſe-breakers, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Robbers, Tories and Banditti: and no Prince can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100623:15"/>to commiſſion theſe perſons, but ſuch as <hi>Nero,</hi> who wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had but one Neck, that he with his own hand might be the Executioner of his own people: ſuch, whoſe inſamous Cowardize maketh way for their Cruelty.</p>
            <p>'Tis fit for him who dares not ſee his Enemy in the Field, to attack him by Ruſſians in his <hi>Winter Quarters:</hi> i. e. his Park, his Garden, his Houſe, or naked in his Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and yet if we may believe the dying Speeches of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Cut-throats, who to gain their own Abſolution from the Prieſt are forced to abſolve their Maſters, ſince <hi>Granval</hi> is dead, and <hi>Du Mont</hi> almoſt forgotten, there are now no more Ruffians remaining beyond the Seas.</p>
            <p>But this Aſſaſſination was timed to the Popiſh Carneval, the preparation to their holy Faſt of <hi>Lent</hi> was to have been a Riot in the Blood of our excellent Prince; a fit Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for that barbarous Act of Religion they were to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit when their Faſt ſhould be ended, which is to eat the Fleſh and Drink the Blood of our Redeemer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brutus</hi> the firſt aroſe againſt <hi>Tarquin,</hi> the ſecond againſt <hi>Caeſar, Piſo</hi> againſt <hi>Nero,</hi> becauſe thoſe Princes were the known Enemies of publick Liberty. And if a Sovereign Prince ſhall ſo far degenerate from the Character of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Country, as to make it his buſineſs to ſubvert the Religion, Laws, and Liberties thereof; in ſuch a caſe a People are not only permitted, but obliged by the duty they owe to their Country, their Poſterity, and their own Souls effectually, by open force of Arms, to remove the cauſe of ſuch an inſupportable Calamity, as being fully aſſured, both from the goodneſs of the divine Nature, as well as from the expreſs word of God, that the Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God only for good: but to commit a Parricide upon ſuch a Prince, who defends not only the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>Europe,</hi> is a greater Villany than what was ever thought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by <hi>Cataline.</hi> How dear ſhould that Life be to us which was ſo barbarouſly ſought after by the profeſſed Enemies of all that is dear to God and Man? how does it become us to be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100623:16"/>thankfull, that <hi>the breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord was not taken in their Pits, of whom we ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder his ſhadow we ſhall live among the Heathen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, They who were bringing this Plague up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, did not intend that it ſhould viſit us ſingle; an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection at Home, and an Invaſion from Abroad were to have been its Attendants.</p>
            <p>That the natural Enemy of <hi>England</hi> ſhould invade and hold Correſpondence to ſtrengthen his deſign is not ſtrange, (altho' carrying on that Correſpondence to an Aſſaſſination be ſome diminution to his Glory.) Nor is it to be admired that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts, who by the tye of their Religion are u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to a foreign Head, ſhould forget the Land of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. Nor is it a wonder, that they who can believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Senſes, ſhould perſuade themſelves, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. may found an Invaſion in ſelf-denial, and at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of <hi>French</hi> Blood, make a Conqueſt upon <hi>England,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſtore <hi>James</hi> the II. But 'tis aſtoniſhing, that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, of the beſt and pureſt Reformation (as they themſelves aſſert) ſhould be Harbingers to the eldeſt Son of Antichriſt: and by an unnatural Conſpiracy prepare the way for the grand <hi>Nimrod,</hi> the mighty Hunter after <hi>Europe</hi>'s Liberty: and aſſiſt him to ſettle the French Yoke upon their native Country: <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſuppreſs the Liberty, burn the Body, poyſon (and as much as in him lieth) damn the Soul of the Nation. For theſe are the certain and known effects of a French Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>What could the great Oppreſſor mean but to found <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> a Title to <hi>England</hi> in Conqueſt? and how inviting has it of late bin to him to know how fond we have (ſome of us) bin of that Title? eſpecially when crown'd with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Settlement: And what other thing could be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, when the Embarking Army had not one <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>Iriſh</hi> Troop in it, being made up only of the <hi>Veteran</hi> Troops of <hi>France,</hi> but that the late King of unhappy memory might march through his former Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100623:16"/>in ſafe Cuſtody, having only the revenge to ſee <hi>England</hi> become the worſt of all Conqueſts, a French Conqueſt? For to the French Monarch alone 'tis owing, that War is made more barbarous than 'twas ever known in former Ages. His Promiſes and Oaths make way for his Perjury, his Treachery leads on to his Cruelty, and what the Sword is uncapable to devour the Fire muſt conſume. Did ever any Men before now found an Inſurrection only in a revenge upon their own native Country? Did ever Men before now form a Rebellion without any other rational proſpect but of Slavery to the Souls and Bodies of themſelves and their Poſterity? May not <hi>England</hi> with aſtoniſhment take up the words of <hi>Iſaiah? Hear O Heavens! and give ear O Earth! I have nouriſhed and brought up Children, and they have rebelled againſt me,</hi> Iſa. 1.2.</p>
            <p>But what does the ſenſe of our wonderfull Deliverance call for? Does it not,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt engage all thoſe who joyn together in a juſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of this unnatural Confederacy to unite together in bonds of mutual love and charity to each other? are not all thoſe who have the ſame common Enemies even thereby compelled to <hi>aſſociate</hi> themſelves together in the ſtricteſt Friendſhip? have not French Invaſions already joyn'd diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Nations of differing Religions, together in one common League for mutual ſafety? and may not the ſame reaſon prevail for the Union of Proteſtants of the ſame Nation (at leaſt) in brotherly love and charity? When the Heathen and the high Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> conſpired together againſt the life of Chriſt, was it not a warning to all his Servants to unite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their confederated Enemies? Certainly when the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our mutual agreement with one another are ſo weighty (as hath bin ſhewn) and the cauſes of our differences ſo very light, nothing but our own ill nature can give an ill turn to the ſcale.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> This Deliverance calls us to more caution, that we give no further Encouragements to the common Oppreſſor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100623:17"/>to invade, nor to the home-bred Traytor to aſſiſt him. Let us no longer preſerve as ſacred the forſeited Right of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and no longer refuſe to own the legal Right of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer. A Right by Law ſhould be (if poſſible) more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to us than a Right by Succeſſion, ſince fortuitous birth giveth a Right by Succeſſion, but 'tis the addition of Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Merit to Princely birth which recommends to a Right by Law. And what greater affront can we offer to the high Merit of our excellent Prince, who uſeth his juſt Title only to ſupport the true old legal Monarchy of <hi>England,</hi> than to pay any reſpect to the Title or Memory of him who Abdicated the Crown? <hi>i. e.</hi> caſt off the legal form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ruled us by a Deſpotick Power; was it though decent or indeed tolerable to preſerve a reſpect for <hi>Tarquin</hi> in the Conſulſhip of <hi>Brutus,</hi> by whoſe Aid the People caſt off the Yoke of his inſupportable Tyranny? but what would have been thought of thoſe, who ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly diſavow the Right of <hi>Brutus</hi> to that high Dignity which the People had veſted in him out of reſpect to <hi>Tarquin</hi> the depoſed Prince?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Let us bleſs God who brought Light out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that by the diſcovery of this unnatural Conſpiracy, he hath ſprang a light, whereby his ſacred Majeſty, and thoſe who are entruſted with any part of the Government under him, may clearly diſcern their Friends from their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and certainly know who are for and who are againſt the conjunct Intereſt of King and People; ſo that from hence ſuch meaſures may be taken which are abſolutely needfull to ſecure our Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever refuſeth to acknowledge the Right of <hi>William</hi> the III. does actually declare for the extinguiſhed Right of <hi>James</hi> the II. and whoſoever owns his Right, muſt by Virtue of his Allegiance hold himſelf in conſcience oblig'd to endeavour his Reſtoration. Now I appeal to all the world, if any ſuch perſon as this can of right claim to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much as Protection from the preſent Government;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100623:17"/>but on the other ſide, every one muſt own that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in protecting them, doth fully diſcharge the higheſt duty of Chriſtian Charity, which is to love our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and do good to thoſe that hate us. Protection is the higheſt Favour which the Government can, in this caſe, beſtow, or which theſe men are fit to receive; for Chriſt never commanded us to truſt our Enemies; but, on the contrary, to temper the Innocency of the Dove with the Wiſdom of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>He who thinks himſelf obliged in Conſcience to <hi>James</hi> the II, as his rightfull King, if he hath not the Courage to make one in an Inſurre Stion, nor the hardy baſeneſs to joyn in an Aſſaſſination, yet 'tis manifeſt that he will not oppoſe the former deſign, nor reveal the latter. Now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho to protect ſuch perſons be the higheſt degree of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity, yet to admit them into the Truſts of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not the higheſt degree of Chriſtian Prudence. The Jeſuits, who were convicted of a Helliſh Plot in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. could never, with all their Wit, excuſe or ſo much as extenuate their Treaſon, and therefore they betook themſelves to the laſt Shift, or an impudent Denial. But our late Convicts with greater Effrontery, own and juſtifie their unnatural Conſpiracy, and die glorying in their Treaſon. But was ever any Kingdom ſo fatally divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelf, that the Religion by Law eſtabliſhed, ſhould be an open Enemy to the civil Conſtitution? that what in the Eye of the Law is Treaſon, ſhould, by the Church, be accounted Duty? that whom the Judge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, the Prieſt ſhall abſolve at Execution? for the Impenitence of the Traytors, and Inſolence of the Abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are both juſtifiable (as they pretend) from the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Doctrine concerning Paſſive Obedience, and it muſt indeed be granted, that if <hi>James</hi> the II. had a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and indefeaſible right to our Paſſive Obedience, the right of King <hi>William</hi> the III. to the Crown of theſe Realms could not at this day have been own'd, nor could the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100623:18"/>Conſpirators, even againſt that Life, which (under God) ſupporteth the liberty of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion throughout the World, been found guilty of Treaſon. But do theſe Apoſtates think to impoſe their Paſſive Doctrine of blind Obedience upon the Proteſtant Church and Kingdom of <hi>England?</hi> do they think we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rightly diſtinguiſh this matter? as for inſtance, Paſſive Obedience to the Law of the Land, is the Doctrine of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> Paſſive Obedience to the will of the Prince, is the Doſtrine of <hi>Judas;</hi> a falſe and trayterous Doctrine, whereby all ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Governments and legal Rights are betray'd to arbitrary Power. <hi>Judas</hi> betray'd the perſon of Chriſt to the High-Prieſt of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Paſſive Obedience, to the will of the late King, betrays the Body of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> all true Chriſtians to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore the Profeſſors of this Doctrine have, by the righteous Laws of this Land, ſuffer'd that Puniſhment to which God in his juſt judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Traytor <hi>Judas,</hi> which was, To be hang'd and burſt in the middle. But what can put a ſtop to the unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell'd Inſolence of this Party, unleſs the Parliamentary Aſſociation (which ſubjects theſe hardned Traytors to a juſt Revenge) be wellcomed with the Heart and Hand of the Nation? Hereby every honeſt Man and Lover of his Country may encourage our Confederates abroad, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Minds of all true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> at Home, and we need not doubt, that God will bleſs theſe our honeſt Endeavours in defence of that Religion which is all Charity and Peace; and of that King whoſe only fault perhaps it is, that his own ſafety is not ſo dear to him, as it is, and ever ought to be, to us. Theſe Cautions are abſolutely needfull to preſerve our Rightfull King and righteous Eſtabliſhment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us joyn our Prayers to God, that no falſe Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor vain Jealouſies may prevent or fruſtrate theſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Cautions, which God in Mercy grant, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
